<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>lambdajunkie</title>
    <link>https://lambdajunkie.org/</link>
    <description>Recent content on lambdajunkie</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://lambdajunkie.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A chance for reflection - Motivations</title>
      <link>https://lambdajunkie.org/posts/reflections-part-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lambdajunkie.org/posts/reflections-part-one/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;September 1st marks 16 years since I graduated from University of Illinois with&#xA;my BS in Mathematics &amp;amp; Computer Science, and I entered the software industry&#xA;officially. A lot has changed since then, from how we develop software to how&#xA;we manage software projects, to how software companies are established. So much&#xA;has changed so quickly in the last 16 years that it prompted me to start looking&#xA;back to where the industry was at the time I started, in an effort to understand&#xA;the evolution and more importantly figure out if some modern trends were making&#xA;more sense than others.  I came to a few realizations about this, and I thought&#xA;I&amp;rsquo;d write them down here.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Site Layout</title>
      <link>https://lambdajunkie.org/posts/new-site/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 May 2021 14:18:46 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lambdajunkie.org/posts/new-site/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello blogosphere! Sorry for the long 3 year gap from my last post.&#xA;After a long break during which I completed graduate school as well as&#xA;starting a couple of other study groups for Atlanta Functional Programming,&#xA;I decided to get back into the blogging game. During this time, looking at&#xA;my current blog site and process to publishing new content, I decided to&#xA;first update my site and its layout. Last time I set up the site, I went through&#xA;the following technologies to pick one that would be right for the site:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About Ram Vedam</title>
      <link>https://lambdajunkie.org/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 May 2021 07:53:05 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lambdajunkie.org/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While I rather not make this into a long professional bio, I will start by&#xA;saying I am a seasoned developer. If you would like to know more about my&#xA;experience please refer to my professional profile on LinkedIn for a more&#xA;complete picture.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I code in many languages, although Common Lisp is one of my favorites. I code in&#xA;it for fun and education, although recently I have been looking into do more work&#xA;with it for some side projects. Hopefully, time permitting, these projects and&#xA;ideas will lead to something that I can show all in the blogosphere (if not it&amp;rsquo;ll&#xA;be a github repo for people to fork, and hopefully critique)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
